# 烹汁
Cooking the sauce
# 汁红亮芡
Shiny and brownish
# 虾仁爆鳝片
Asian swamp eel flakes fried with prawns
# 虾爆鳝
# 刚才大爷讲了说
Da Ye was just saying
# 这个菜淮扬菜也有 对老菜
- This dish is also in Huaiyang Cuisine.
- Yes, traditional.
# 这个是杭帮菜
This originally comes from Hangzhou Cuisine.
# 杭州菜实际上也是
Well ‘Hangzhou Cuisine’ was actually
# 过去淮扬菜的一列
A part of ‘Huaiyang Cuisine’.
# 归属于淮扬菜“管辖”
Falls under the category of ‘Huaiyang Cuisine’.
# 因为有大爷做淮扬菜
Since Da Ye is the master of ‘Huaiyang cuisine’
# 我就让大爷看看
I’ll show him what I can do
# 三弟这个菜行不行 很行
To prove myself. ‘Very well’.
# 是炒是爆 爆
- Stir fried or deep fried?
- Deep fried.
# 咱们先调汁 一定要调汁
First we have to make the sauce. It is necessary.
# 一勺两勺 糖 放糖 两勺半
One, two. Two and a half spoons of sugar.
# 小糖醋口 不是大糖醋口
‘Are you going to make it taste sour and sweet just enough?’ ‘Definitely’
# 香醋 镇江香醋
Zhenjiang Vinegar.
# 这颜色深没问题 颜色重
It’s OK if the color looks a bit dark. It should be dark.
# 搁点盐 盐是本 盐还不少呢
- Add some salt. The salt is the base flavor.
- That's quite a lot.
# （白）胡椒粉要大
Also needs a lot of white pepper
# 炒鳝鱼胡椒粉要大 必须得大
- You need to make the flavor of pepper quite heavy if you are cooking this dish.
- We have to.
# 大也不能说太大
But not too heavy.
# 来点老抽 调调色
Dark soy sauce helps to tone the color.
# 颜色就起来了
Now the color looks good.
# 酱油
Light Soy sauce.
# 香油要不要 必须要
- Do we need sesame oil?
- Absolutely.
# 这手还直哆嗦
Why are your hands shaking?
# 紧张了吧 这眼睛还看不见
- You're too nervous.
- My eyes can barely see.
# 盖不上盖儿了还
Can’t even put the lid back.
# 酒 酒最后 黄酒
At the end, rice wine.
# 倒没了 该买了啊
‘No left. Should buy some more’
# 咱们是这样 来点水来点汤
All right then, add some water.
# 这粉子（淀粉）这是技巧
Now this is an important thing.
# 少搁点粉子靠火收
‘Don’t put too much starch in it. Let the heat reduce it.’
# 粉子大了赶紧出 对
‘If you put too much starch, put the wok away and let it simmer.’
# 你说对了
You are right
# 小汁儿兑好 这颜色是不浅点儿啊
Here's the sauce. Is this color too light?
# 我认为稍微浅点
I think so.
# 再搁点老抽吧
Let’s put some more dark soy sauce.
# 这回行了
Now it’s good.
# 浆这个吧 很简单
Let’s marinate the prawns. Nothing fancy.
# 还是酒先
Still, you need rice wine first
# 多了 葫芦 口小肚子大
A little bit too much. The bottle has a large body.
# 还得拿双筷子
And the chopsticks.
# 说一声我给你拿
Tell me and I'll get them for you
# 别介您闪着腰怎么办
Don’t bother, I’m worried about your back.
# 三叔你家这个（酒）没了
San Shu, you are running out of the wine.
# 三叔 我给你放油怎么样
San Shu, shall I pour the oil for you?
# 您先把火灭了吧
Just turn off the fire first.
# 盐 底口
Salt, the base flavor.
# 您说现在为什么虾仁进不去水
Why don't the prawns today absorb any water?
# 它本身就含水量就大 真大
They contain a lot of water in themselves already.
# 你看 越打越出
Exactly. The heavier you stir, the more water comes out
# 没事就拿纸蘸一下
Take some paper towel to wipe it.
# 蘸干水分 加粉子
Dry the water, add the starch.
# 可以 加粉子
Yeah, continue to add the starch.
# 按正常的搁点蛋清咱不搁了
Normally we should add some egg white as well, but we won’t do it today.
# 搁不了 再搁就澥了
Right, otherwise the prawns will be too watery.
# 咱们把鳝鱼加上盐 就是淀粉啊
Let’s put some starch in the swamp eel.
# 这鳝鱼都切好了
Wow, the eel has already been sliced.
# 切好了 趁您没在
Yeah, done while you were not here.
# 你知道他买回来就是斜刀片
You know he bought the slant-cut eel.
# 买的就是去骨的人都给切好了的
It is boneless when you bought it.
# 现在超市真方便
The market now is super convenient.
# 二伯你愿意干活 你搅匀了
Er Bai, you must wanna work. Stir it please
# 我先把这个料头切了
I’ll cut these first.
# 咱这个是红椒青椒 就是配头
These are red pepper and green pepper, as the sides.
# 大爷为什么鳝鱼都不去血
Why you don’t rinse the blood from the swamp eel?
# 都带着血吃
We always cook it with the blood.
# 鳝鱼的血是有营养的
Its blood is full of nutrients.
# 当然为什么要求我们在做鳝鱼的时候
However you definitely cannot use
# S鳝鱼不能用 存放的鳝鱼不能用
Dead eels or those have been stored for a long time.
# 血变质了
The blood has deteriorated.
# 头天的血是鲜红的 第二天血是黑色的
First day you see the red blood, then it turns black on the next day.
# 所以那（第二天的）血就得把它洗了
That’s why you need to clean the blood (on the second day)
# 鳝鱼这血只要一变色
As long as the blood color has changed
# 它的鲜味就没了 而且还腥了
It will lose its umami taste and taste really bad.
# 而且也没有营养了
And no nutrition, neither.
# 因为它变质太快
Because the Asian swamp eel is too easy to get deteriorated.
# 所以我们鳝鱼一定是
Therefore we need to make sure that the eel
# 当天买 当天吃 当天用
Is bought, used and eaten on the same day.
# S甲鱼 S鳝鱼 S螃蟹都不能吃
Anything dead - soft-shelled turtles, swamp eels, crabs - are not edible.
# 咱们先把虾仁滑出来大爷
Okay let’s pan-fry the prawns first
# 为什么先滑虾仁
Why do we prepare the prawns first?
# 虾仁干净 给染了 这个有序
Otherwise the colors will be mixed. The order matters.
# 火大一点 就这么大
Turn the heat higher
# 油温还是差点
The oil is not hot enough.
# 虾仁水分太大 太大了
The prawns contain so much water.
# 还不敢动 你想想
Can't even move. Think about it.
# 咱们这青红椒在油锅里一放
Then the peppers.
# 这一着热就熟了
They get cooked immediately.
# 你知道我现在炒虾仁
You know what I do with the prawns
# 在家里怎么炒么
when cooking at home?
# 我都不过油了 直接用水滑
I don’t even use the oil, I only use water.
# 大家感觉这虾仁
People might feel that the prawns
# 吃起来这虾仁特别的脆
taste really crispy.
# 实际上虾仁没那么脆
Actually it’s not like that.
# 含水量比较高
They are full of water
# 上浆起来效果不会太好
So, the prawns are not easy to starch well.
# 所以我就直接拿水就直接汆了
That’s why I only use water to boil them.
# 效果还不错
It works though.
# 但是老觉得跟油滑的
But, compared to the oil method
# 还是相对有点区别
there's still some difference.
# 还是有点区别 差一点
Still a bit difference
# 油滑的香
Oil gives the aroma.
# 好了这油温可以慢慢去炸
Right now the temperature is enough for the deep frying.
# 这油温多少 五成了
- What’s the temperature now?
- About 150°C.
# 这鳝鱼切的条啊 他切的大长条
- The eel has been sliced already.
- They make the slices really big.
# 他那外边（买）进来的 他就没动
He bought directly from the market
# 我怕大爷还得（收拾）少下少下
I wanted to save some time for Da Ye
# 网友直接就买去了 还省事儿呢
Yeah people now usually do the same way. It's easier.
# 就炸这种颜色 因为它有血
This how the color should be, because it has blood in it.
# 三叔是太聪明了
San Shu is really smart
# 还复油（炸）么 不用复油
- Do you need to re-fry?
- No needs.
# 鳝鱼嫩 你一炸就小了
The eel is so tender that it cannot be overcooked, it will shrink.
# 把它的肉炸硬了 一次成活
Deep fry the eel only once.
# 这鳝鱼不少
There is quite a lot
# 现在已经就等于是出锅了这菜
Now the dish is already finished
# 留一点底油
Leave some base oil.
# 你看看亮子 把它倒回来了
Look, Liangzi. Now we put it back.
# 一烹汁 齐活
Finish it with the sauce
# 瞧这碗儿好使
See how nice this bowl is
# 开火 看见没有 烹汁儿
Turn the heat on, adding the sauce now
# 明汁亮芡 把盘拿过来
The sauce is so shiny and thick, pass me the plate please
# 这盘儿小点儿 小点儿就是它了
- Is this plate too small?
- It should work.
# 给点明油
And some oil
# 汁红亮芡
Check this color
# 星星点点 好漂亮
How beautiful it is!
# 真蹿啊 漂亮漂亮
Yeah really good and pretty
# 大爷这是最后的一道 最经典的
And now the very last step
# 这是我最关键的一点
The most important thing is
# （白）胡椒粉 最后撒胡椒粉
White pepper. Drop the white pepper
# 炒的里边还有 里外两次
Remember to add the pepper twice
# 所以胡椒粉用的量非常大
So we'll use quite a lot of it
# 大爷你自己尝吧 来了
- Da Ye, come and taste it.
- Will do!
# 我就不
I don't.
# 快接着亮子
Come on, Liangzi
# 你看像不像红烧海参那样子
Look! Doesn't this look like the braised sea cucumber?
# 香
Smells so good
# 怎么样这菜做的 确实够意思吧
How’s my dish? Quite a classic right?
# 三叔聪明
San Shu is really smart indeed.
# 过去鳝鱼它是上浆滑油
In the past days we cooked it by starching and then stir-frying.
# 他改成了一个炸的方法
But he changed it to the deep-fried way.
# 炸的方法呢鳝鱼更加滑嫩
This method makes the swamp eel taste more smooth
# 而且它就特别丰满
And it didn't shrink
# 有一个保护层
It has a protection layer.
# 就跟穿着衣服似的
Just like with ‘clothes’
# 另外挂汁着味 覆味覆的好
Plus the sauce covers and stays on the eel.
# 再加上他拿汁拿芡拿的挺准
He controlled the heat to make the starch thicken perfectly.
# 所以你看特别亮
That’s why it looks so shiny
# 出锅的时候再点点香油 更显着亮
It’ll looks brighter if you add some sesame oil when you bring it to the table
# 胡椒粉再多点 更好吃
And more pepper
# 所以按照中国的英语的话说
So in the Chinese way to speak English
# 非常好
Very good
# 再来一块
One more please
# 谢谢小亮默默的付出
Thanks for Liangzi, for your help.
# 谢谢三叔辛苦了
Thank you San Shu for the hard work.
# 谢谢大爷精彩的点评
Thank you Da Ye, for your great comments.
# 然后呢
And what else?
# 大爷 三叔 小亮子
Da Ye, San Shu, Liangzi
# 对不起了我先拿走了
Sorry I’ll just take them all
# import ending.srt 00:07:52,190